Finding Aid for Harvey Ovshinsky papers, 1948-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harvey Ovshinsky papers
1948-2014
Ovshinsky, Harvey.
2015038 Aa 2 AC
Writer, journalist, news broadcaster, radio host, television producer, creative consultant, and teacher in Detroit, Mich. Includes materials related to Ovshinsky's founding of Detroit's first underground newspaper, The Fifth Estate, as well as photographs, correspondence, writings, personal memorabilia, legal materials, press articles, topical files, transcripts and audiovisual materials representing Ovshinsky's work in radio and television from the 1960s through the 2000s.
12.7 linear feet
1 oversize boxes
3 oversize volumes
4.22 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, Univeristy of Michigan
Donated by Harvey Ovshinsky (donor no. 10907 ), in June 2014 and December 2014.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Harvey Ovshinsky was born on April 9, 1948 to Stanford and Norma Ovshinsky and grew up in northwest Detroit, Mich. From an early age, Ovshinsky exhibited a passion for writing. Shortly after his parents' divorce in 1959, Stanford Ovshinsky and his second wife Iris gave Ovshinsky a small printing press, enabling him to print his own newsletters. While attending Mumford High school, Ovshinsky continued to write and self-publish. He also worked after school at Mumford Music, a neighborhood music store owned by his mother's second husband, Adolph Marks. Ovshinsky thrived on the experience of the diverse community that frequented the music store. Further, working at Mumford Music strengthened the teenaged Ovshinsky's sense of connection with the culture of Detroit. He was devastated when his mother and stepfather decided to move their family to Los Angeles in 1965.
While in Los Angeles, Ovshinsky worked with the LA Free Press, one of the most broadly distributed underground newspapers of the 1960s. This job, combined with homesickness, sparked his dream to found a similar newspaper in Detroit. He returned home that same year and founded The Fifth Estate, Detroit's first underground newspaper. Ovshinsky briefly attended Monteith College at Wayne State University in Detroit while simultaneously running the newspaper, but eventually dropped his classes to focus on The Fifth Estate. The fledgling newspaper expanded with the help of anti-war activist Peter Werbe and the Detroit Committee to End the War in Vietnam.
Ovshinsky left The Fifth Estate in April 1968. By the time of his departure, most of the staff held more radical views than Ovshinsky, who was more interested in promoting community and communication than social revolution. Ovshinsky began two years of alternative service work as a conscientious objector at the Lafayette Clinic, a state psychiatric hospital in Detroit. He started as a clerk and worked his way up to Attendant Nurse. While at Lafayette, he founded an independent self-help center called "Open City," intended to provide counseling, community, and medical and legal support to Detroit's youth. During his time at Lafayette Clinic, Ovshinsky also met his future wife, Cathie Kurek, who was working there as a psychiatric nurse.
While still employed at the clinic, Ovshinsky launched a weekly morning talk show called Spare Change in 1969, which aired on an alternative Detroit radio station, WXYZ-FM. He was hired as news director at WABX-FM in Detroit the following year. Ovshinsky's work in media and communications soon expanded to television, when he left WABX and joined The Video Group in 1973 as a writer and producer.
Quickly frustrated by the financial instability of The Video Group, Ovshinsky launched his own company, Creative Media Inc., in 1974, providing freelance writing and production services to businesses, advertising agencies, and television stations. While he enjoyed the freedom of working independently, financial difficulties led him to close the company in 1976 and return to work for a local television station, WXYZ-TV, in Detroit. In the decade to follow, Ovshinsky would continue to work on projects in both television and radio for stations such as WDIV-TV, WRIF-FM, and Detroit Public Television.
In the early 1980s, Ovshinsky began writing original screenplays. These include PJ and the Dragon and The Keyman. In 1980, Ovshinsky also began teaching to bring in extra income for his own children's education. While working with elementary school children at Grosse Pointe Academy, Ovshinsky developed a passion for understanding how children learn through play, drawing, and dramatization, which led to his development of a proprietary approach to teaching through "physual" (physical plus visual) learning. This passion would later carry over to his efforts to create educational programming for children, such as Pendragon's Park and The Mighty Hubble. Ovshinsky also taught courses in screenwriting and creative writing at the university level, lecturing at the College for Creative Studies, Wayne State University, Madonna University, and Washtenaw Community College.
In 1986, Ovshinsky founded HKO Media, which afforded him the opportunity to work on productions with a variety of clients, including former employers such as WTVS, WDIV-TV, and WXYZ-TV. With HKO, he was also able to realize his dream of producing "local-for-national" documentaries about Detroit, including Voodoo Man of Heidelberg Street (1990), Close to Home -- The Tammy Bocommino Story (1992), and The Last Hit: Children and Violence (1997). HKO Media productions received some of the highest awards in broadcasting, including a National Emmy and a George Foster Peabody Award fo r Close to Home -- The Tammy Bocommino Story, and an Alfred I. DuPont-Columbia University Award for The Last Hit: Children and Violence.
During the economic recession of 2006 in Michigan, Ovshinsky transformed HKO Media from a production company into a creative consulting service. As a creative consultant, Ovshinsky received a commission from Family Communications Inc. to create a PBS children's series to replace Mr. Rogers' Neighborhood, which resulted Ovshinsky's work on The Mighty Hubble. Ovshinsky closed HKO Media in 2012.
The collection is divided into four series: Personal files, Professional files, Project files, and Audiovisual materials.
The collection traces Harvey Ovshinsky's personal and professional development as a writer, journalist, news broadcaster, radio host, television producer, creative consultant, and teacher. The Personal files include autobiographical writings providing insights into the events in Ovshinsky's childhood and adolescence that led to his early interest in writing and journalism. The Professional files contain the first issues of The Fifth Estate, and extensive memorabilia and press coverage on various radio stations and video and television production companies where Ovshinsky was employed. This series encompasses material on the history of Detroit's counterculture in the 1960s and 1970s. The Project files also include topical files on Detroit culture and history, which inspired many of Ovshinsky's documentaries and creative writing.
Materials from Ovshinsky's teaching career and transcripts from his speaking engagements in the Professional files reveal his approach to teaching writing, while drafts for films, stories, and television series in the Project files offer a view into Ovshinsky's creative process. Files named "War Dances" appear throughout both the Professional files and the Project files series. "War Dances" were an integral part of Ovshinsky's approach to both problem solving and the creative process. "War Dances" were personal notes and reflections in which Ovshinsky assessed his present situation, identified his goals and imagined paths to the solution of a problem or to the final stages of a project. Materials from the subseries Educational and children's properties in the Project files include extensive topical files from Ovshinsky's research on how children learn through play. Samples of Ovshinsky's work in radio, television, educational programming and public speaking are available in Audiovisual materials.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.); Fifth Estate.; HKO Media (Firm); Journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; Ovshinsky, Harvey.; Radio broadcasting--Michigan--Detroit.; Radio journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; Radio producers and directors--Michigan--Detroit.; Television journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; Television producers and directors--Michigan--Detroit.; Television programs--Michigan--Detroit.; Television stations--Michigan--Detroit.; Underground press publications--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Detroit (Mich.)
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Detroit (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
16mm.; Audiocassettes.; Betacam-SP.; Digital file formats.; Film reels.; Magnetic tapes.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.; Videocassettes.
- Personal Files
  The Personal files series (0.6 linear feet, 1948-2015 with gaps) consists of two groupings: Childhood and High School. The Childhood group includes photographs, correspondence, an ephemera collection of monster movie ads, diaries, and samples of Ovshinsky's earliest writing and first newsletters. The High School group contains memorabilia from Ovshinsky's high school years, including photographs, personal writings, an independent literary magazine, and yearbooks. Folders in this series include Ovshinsky's own reflections on his childhood and adolescence. The series also contains Ovshinsky's preface to the collection, contained in a file labeled "Inventory and backstories." This file provides Ovshinsky's description of the contents of the collection and a detailed account of his life experiences from his perspective in 2015. However, although the order of materials remains the same, the box numbers indicated in Ovshinsky's description are obsolete; please refer to the contents list below to locate files.
  - Inventory and backstories, 2015 (Box 1)
  - Childhood
    - Bow Elementary school memorabilia, undated (Box 1)
    - Letters to Norma Ovshinsky, 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - Writings, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters, circa, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Monster Movie Advertisements, undated (Box 1)
    - Family photographs, 1949-1961; 4 folders
      - Akron, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - Greenfield Avenue and 19935 Forrer Street, 1950-1961 (Box 14)
      - Camp Tanuga, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - High School
    - Henry Ford High School, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Mumford memorabilia, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Writings, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 14)
    - Short Monster Film, 1964; .ZIP and .MP4 files
    - The IDiom, 1965 (Box 1)
      Independent literary magazine
    - Yearbooks, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
- Professional Files
  The Professional files series (3 linear feet, 1965-2012) contains print materials that trace the developments of Ovshinsky's career in journalism, communications media, and teaching. The series is divided into six subseries: Underground journalism and The Fifth Estate; Civilian service as conscientious objector; Radio print materials and memorabilia; Video and television production print materials and memorabilia, Teaching; and Speaking engagements, presentations, and workshops. The series is comprised of press articles, photographs, professional correspondence, project files, and Ovshinsky's writings, notes, and personal reflections. The Underground journalism and The Fifth Estate subseries contains correspondence, personal memoirs, and writing on Detroit's counterculture in the late sixties through the early seventies. This subseries also includes the earliest issues of The Fifth Estate. The Civilian service as conscientious objector subseries focuses on the founding of Open City, a clinical self-help center providing social, medical and legal support to Detroit's youth. The Radio print materials and memorabilia subseries consists of scripts, photographs, and press articles. The Video and television production print materials and memorabilia subseries contains photographs, press articles, correspondence, and an extensive collection of records from Ovshinsky's own production and consulting company, HKO Media. The Teaching subseries is comprised of student evaluations, course materials, correspondence, and Ovshinsky's reflections on teaching writing. The Speaking engagements, presentations, and workshops group is a collection of promotional materials as well as Ovshinsky's preparatory notes, outlines, or complete texts of presentations and speeches.
  - Underground Journalism and The Fifth Estate
    - Los Angeles, 1965; 2 folders (Box 1)
      Includes correspondence, writings about L.A. Free Press, and 2012 student thesis on counterculture in L.A. by Andrew Ernest Ligeti
    - Monteith College at Wayne State University, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Fifth Estate Materials
      - War Dance, circa, 1965 (Box 1)
      - Media coverage, 1967-1985 (Box 1)
      - Photographs, 1965-1975 (Box 1)
    - Harvey's "Red" Files, 1966-1971 (Box 1)
      Detroit Police Department files
    - Memoir materials, 1965-2008; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Outgoing to Norma and Adolph Marks, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
      - The Fifth Estate, 2005-2008 (Box 1)
    - Fifth Estate memorabilia, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
    - Back Issues of The Fifth Estate, November 1965-March 1969; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Civilian service as Conscientious Objector
    - Writings, 1967-1972 (Box 2)
    - Open City War Dance and Picture, undated (Box 2)
    - Press articles on Open City, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Radio Print Materials and Memorabilia
    - WXYZ-FM's Spare Change radio show, undated (Box 2)
    - WABX memorabilia, circa 1970-1973 (Box 2)
    - WABX press articles, circa 1971-1983 (Box 2)
    - WABX newscast scripts, circa 1971-1973 (Box 2)
    - WABX photographs, circa 1968-1971 (Box 2)
    - WDET/WRIF/WCSX press articles, 1987-1993 (Box 2)
    - WDET/WRIF photographs and memorabilia, circa 1980-1995 (Box 2)
    - WDET consulting materials, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Video and Television Production Print Materials and Memorabilia
    - Barrington Bunny scrapbook, circa, 1974 (Volume 1)
    - Video Group photographs and press articles, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Creative Media memorabilia, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - WXYZ-TV press articles, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - WXYZ-TV photographs, undated (Box 2)
    - WXYZ-TV memorabilia, circa, 1976-1980 (Box 2)
    - WDIV-TV press articles and press credentials, circa, 1977-1988 (Box 2)
    - WDIV-TV photographs, undated (Box 2)
    - Detroit Public Television press articles and press credentials, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - WXYZ-TV scrapbook, 1979-1980 (Volume 2)
    - WDIV-TV scrapbook, 1982 (Volume 3)
    - HKO Media (Box 2)
      - Press articles, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
      - Press articles, 1995-2008 (Box 2)
      - Photographs and production stills, 1976-2004 (Box 2)
      - Resumes, circa, 1974-2009 (Box 2)
      - Writings, circa, 1988-2009 (Box 2)
      - HKO Media internship manual, 2005 (Box 2)
      - WTVS proposals and co-productions, 1987-1993 (Box 2)
      - Professional correspondence, 1997-2010; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Project files, 1990-1997
        - The Night Martin Luther King Came to Grosse Point, 1990 (Box 3)
          Includes photographs
        - Alex Manoogian, Portrait of a Man of Charity, 1991 (Box 3)
        - Off the Wall, 1997 (Box 3)
      - Letter of Proposal to Michigan State University, 2008 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence
        - Pace, Bill, circa, 2006-2009 (Box 3)
        - Martin, Norean, 2004-2012 (Box 3)
      - WTVS War Dances, 1989 (Box 3)
      - War Dances, 1988-2010 (Box 3)
  - Teaching
    - Student evaluations, with gaps, 1986-2013 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1982-2014 (Box 8)
    - Personal notes and correspondence, 1998-2012 (Box 8)
    - Grosse Pointe Academy memorabilia, 1993-2002 (Box 8)
    - High school screenwriting workshop, undated (Box 8)
    - College course materials, 1996-2013; 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Writings on writing, circa, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Speaking Engagements, Presentations, and Workshops
    - Press releases and articles, 1986-2011 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, circa, 1992-2010 (Box 8)
    - The Role of the Producer in Broadcast and Cable Television, Cranbrook, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Directing and Producing Documentary Films, 1988 (Box 9)
    - The Documentary Producer as Storyteller, Detroit Producer's Association, circa 1988 (Box 9)
    - The Craft of the Documentary Producer, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Winning Awards by Becoming a Better Producer, Oakland County Cable Communications Corporation, 1990 (Box 9)
    - Producing Talk Shows that Say Something, Oakland County Cable Communications Corporation, 1990 (Box 9)
    - The Lawyer as Storyteller, State Bar of Michigan, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Storytellers, Wayne County Advance, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Keynote, Silver Circle Awards, Detroit Chapter of National Association of Television Arts and Sciences, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Keynote, Michigan Television/Video Student Conference, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Lessons from the Creative Journey, Shir Shalom synagogue, 1995 (Box 9)
    - Creative Writing Weekend for Adults, Grosse Pointe Memorial, 1995 (Box 9)
    - Eulogy for Michigan sculptor Arthur Schneider, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Cornerstone grade school, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Inside the Secret Garden; An Intimate Look at the Creative Process, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Royal Oak Rotary, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Adat Shalom: Creativity and Peace: A Writer's Perspective, 1998 (Box 9)
    - Chapel Talk to students, Grosse Pointe Academy, 1998 (Box 9)
    - HKO Salute to Stanford Ovshinsky, Detroit Chapter of Workmen's Circle, 1999 (Box 9)
    - Keynote, Critical Viewers' Project, Detroit Chapter of National Association of Television Arts and Sciences, 2001 (Box 9)
    - Detroit Music Awards, 2001 (Box 9)
    - Digital Arts, Film and Television Festival, 2001; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - The Art of Engaging Young Writers in the Classroom, National Council of Teachers of English, 2004 (Box 9)
    - An Idea Is Not a Story: How to Focus Your Message to Media and Donors, Nonprofit Enterprises at Work, 2004 (Box 9)
    - An Idea Is Not a Story: How to Focus Your Message to Media and Donors, Association of Professional Fundraisers--Greater Detroit Chapter, 2004 (Box 9)
    - How to Produce a Successful Career in Filmmaking, Detroit Docs International Film Festival, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Do I Have to Leave Detroit? How to Make a Hometown Career, Detroit Docs International Film Festival, 2005 (Box 9)
    - Eight Words or Less: Creating Taglines That Can Help Your Business Grow, Lutheran Social Services of Michigan, 2005 (Box 9)
    - An Idea Is Not a Story: How to Focus Your Message to Media and Donors, Campus Compact, 2005 (Box 9)
    - Once Upon a Team: The Power of Story in the Workplace, National Council of Teachers of English, 2006 (Box 9)
    - How to Use Storytelling to Build Relationships in Business, INFORUM, 2007 (Box 9)
    - An Idea Is Not a Story, Michigan State University, 2007 (Box 9)
    - Telling Our Story in Eight Words or Less, Ozone House, 2008 (Box 9)
    - Ozone House Video Production workshop, 2008 (Box 9)
    - An Idea Is Not a Story, Michigan Student Film and Video Festival, 2008 (Box 9)
    - PAH-Festival Keynote: The 60% Incentive; The Other Reason Why We Make Movies and Tell Our Stories in Michigan, 2009 (Box 9)
    - Writing for the Movies, Chelsea District Library, 2010 (Box 9)
    - How to Produce a Career in Video and Film Production, Eastern Michigan University, 2010 (Box 9)
    - Screenwriting weekend, 2010 (Box 9)
    - Association for Women in Communications, 2010 (Box 9)
    - The Backdoor Approach to Selling Your First Screenplay, Flint Film Festival, 2010 (Box 9)
    - How to Be a Great Backpack Video Journalist, Asian American Journalists' Association, 2011 (Box 9)
    - If You Can Write It, You Can Shoot It: A Beginner's Guide to Video Storytelling, The Community House of Birmingham, 2011 (Box 9)
    - Macomb Community College, 2011 (Box 9)
    - Today I am an Erasure and Other Lessons Learned from Jewish Writers, Ann Arbor Jewish Cultural Society, 2011 (Box 9)
    - How to Write Your First Screenplay in Six Months, Ann Arbor Screenwriters' Group, 2011-2012 (Box 9)
    - The Entrepreneur as Storyteller, University of Michigan, 2012 (Box 9)
- Project Files
  The Project files series (5.1 linear feet, 1983-2011) is divided into three subseries: Screenplays, Educational and children's properties, and Miscellaneous unproduced projects and properties. This series encompasses extensive collections of drafts, notes, topical and research files, and correspondence, providing a glimpse into Ovshinsky's personal creative process as well as the production process. The Screenplays subseries includes drafts, correspondence, interviews, feedback, topical files, Writers' Guild registrations, and legal materials. The Educational and children's properties subseries contains topical files on child psychology, proposals, correspondence, creative notes and production materials relating to Ovshinsky's three major projects for children: Pendragon's Park, Please Don't Eat the Books, and The Mighty Hubble. Miscellaneous unproduced projects and properties include summaries of story concepts, drafts, and topical files.
  - Screenplays
    - PJ and the Dragon
      - Topical files, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
        File originally titled "Magic Dragon letters to PJ and original posting in church bulletin"
      - Press articles, 1982 (Box 3)
      - Early drafts and notes, 1983 (Box 3)
      - Research interviews, undated (Box 3)
      - Screenplay drafts, 1986-1996; 7 folders (Box 3)
      - International Creative Management correspondence, 1986-1996 (Box 3)
      - Longbow Productions correspondence and casting notes, 1987-1994 (Box 3)
      - Longbow Productions correspondence, 1987-2009 (Box 3)
      - Legal, 1984-1988 (Box 3)
    - Max Maxwell's Miracle Script, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - The Keyman
      - Topical files, (1 of 2 folders), 1982-2009 (Box 3)
        Includes photographs of Lesley Payne and WDIV-TV documentary script that inspired the screenplay
      - Topical files, (2 of 2 folders), 1982-2009 (Box 4)
      - Flying instructions from Philip Handleman, undated (Box 4)
      - Notes and sketches, 1987-1989 (Box 4)
      - Writers' Guild registrations, 1987-2012 (Box 4)
      - Harlo Productions miscellaneous materials, 1990-1996 (Box 4)
      - Pitching (with correspondence), 1993-2011 (Box 4)
      - Feedback, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
      - Screenplay drafts, 1992-2010; 10 folders (Box 4)
  - Educational and Children's Properties
    - Pendragon's Fire and Pendragon's Park
      - Story drafts, 2000-2009 (Box 4)
      - Pilot script, 1998 (Box 4)
      - Outline for musical, 2000 (Box 4)
      - War Dances, 1998-2003 (Box 4)
      - Bob Kernen and Movement Marketing Correspondence, 2001-2007 (Box 4)
      - Proposals and correspondence, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
      - Proposals and correspondence, 2005-2010 (Box 4)
      - Proposals and requests for funding, 1999-2006; 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Legal, 1998-2006 (Box 5)
      - Pendragon Park video production materials, 2002; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Pendragon website design, circa, 2002 (Box 5)
      - Design book, undated (Box 5)
      - Graphics, 2003-2007 (Box 5)
      - Teaching Philosophy Statements, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
      - Curriculum, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
      - Pendragon Park "Visitor's Guide", 2004 (Box 5)
      - Presentations, 2003-2011
        - "The Magic in Me," Colorado Language Arts Society, 2003 (Box 5)
        - "The Pendragon Path to Creative Writing," Association of Independent Michigan Schools, 2003 (Box 5)
        - "The Art of Engaging Young Writers," National Council of Teachers of English, 2004 (Box 5)